the recording is running and so as you
can see today we have a guest lecturer
we have a shun mistre Asian misra is a
research scientist at Facebook AI
research fair where he works on computer
vision and machine learning his research
interest is in reducing the need for
supervision in visual learning
I finished his PhD at the robotics
Institute at the Carnegie Mellon
University where he worked with Martin
help Hobart and Abhinav Gupta his PhD
thesis was about I was titled visual
learning with minimal human supervision
for which he received the SCS
distinguished dissertation award so in
2018 so with less how to say with
further ado I don't have to speak
English let's get we cannot even have
the round of applause you know can we
have like in the chat round of applause
for our speaker so everyone my name is
Isha I'll be talking about self
supervised learning in computer vision
today and a lot of the focus is actually
going to be sort of more on the
discriminative style of approaches and
it's not really going to be on
generative set of approaches and I sort
of go about it more and more as I go
into my talk so this sort of success
story for representation learning or
like computer vision so far has been
clearly this sort of pre training step
or the imagenet moment of like computer
vision so what has worked really well is
that when we have a large label data set
like image net we can learn a
representation by performing an image
classification task on this large data
set and what is very useful is not just
performing this particular task at hand
but to take these representations that
you learn and they're to use them for
downstream tasks where you may not have
enough label data and this has worked
really really well and sort of them also
standard recipe of success
now the so this really involves
collecting a large dataset of supervisor
images and you need to get a bunch of
these large diverse images and label
them with a bunch of large diverse
concepts so let's try to first see
whether we can sort of collect these
labels and what are sort of the
difficulties in doing so so the image
net data set is a very sort of small
data set in the grander scheme of things
for example image net just has 14
million images and it has roughly 22,000
concepts and just labeling this entire
thing if you look at the amount of
effort that was spent it's about 22
human years to label this entire dataset
for contrast a lot of people started
looking at these alternative supervision
approaches where you are predicting
something like not really a very sort of
pristine nice label but something which
is more easy to get for example predict
like hashtags or to take GPS locations
of images or what we're going to really
focus on in this lecture is going to be
about Excel supervised learning which is
going to be using the data itself so the
first question that I always like to
sort of start out with is why why don't
you just like get labels for all your
data why do you even want to invent this
entire line of research why not just get
all the labels so I did this small
exercise where I plotted the amount of
supervision that we have for vision data
sets so what I did is basically I'd
looked at all the images which have
bounding boxes and so these are images
where you know what kind of concepts are
in the image and you also have a box
drawn around them and this is sort of
the standard thing to do for something
like an object detection model so if you
look at all the data sets in vision that
have bounding boxes you'll get roughly
about a million or so images now if you
relax this constraint and you say that
okay I don't really care about where the
object is located all I care about is
what objects are located what objects
are present in the image and so if you
relax that constraint you immediately
get an order of magnitude more data so
you basically get about that yeah about
40 million images or so
now if you further sort of relax this
constraint and you say that I don't
really care about this image level
supervision either all I care about is
internet internet pictures that are
present you get basically about five
orders of magnitude more amount of data
and so if you look at this plot now you
can see immediately that the amount of
data that we have which is labeled even
at a bounding box or an image level is
basically nothing compared to what
images exist on in the internet scale
and I haven't really forgotten these
images like forgotten the bars on the
left hand side it's just that they
completely disappear and you really need
to make this plot something like a log
plot to actually even get these bars to
appear so now of course internet photos
do not represent everything about the
world there are things that really
require motion or things that really
require other physical senses to learn
so in the real world there are going to
be far more things that you actually
experience far more sensory inputs that
you can get and it's really hard to
obtain labels for all this data and
again to put things in perspective
imagenet which is just for teens in
images and with a very small number of
concepts that you have required a lot of
time the label so clearly labeling is
not really going to scale to either all
of Internet photos or even the real
world so the other sort of problem with
labeling is that for complex concepts
like video it's just really hard to sort
of scale labeling the second problem is
that rare concepts sort of are really
hard to label so for example this is one
of the popular image data sets called
label me and over here we can see that
if you look at the kinds of concepts you
observe there are a lot of concepts that
are so rare that you're going to have
the label a lot of data to even get a
few instances of these concepts so in
this data set 10% of the classes account
for more than 93% of the data which
already tells you that in order to sort
of scale labeling to like more and more
concepts you'll need a lot and lot more
data with very diminishing returns so
this is sort of the standard long-tailed
problem
and of course pre-training is not right
always the right thing to do for example
if you just completely change your
domain to now move it to say medical
imaging it's not clear whether a
missionary training is the right sort of
thing for this task or if you do not
know sort of the downstream tasks a
priority how do you collect a big data
set and how do you do this entire free
training a downstream task fine evening
recipe so self supervised loading sort
of comes in between and it tries to give
you an alternate way to pre train your
models or to learn from data or learn
from experiences without requiring
pristine supervision so in this case so
there are sort of two simple definitions
that you can come up with for self
supervised learning the first is more
from like a discriminative or like a
supervised training perspective so in
imagenet for example you have an image
and you can it can be classified into
one of thousand levels so self to
provide everything can be thought of as
a way to obtain labels from the data
using an automatic process so that
automatic process does not really
require a lot of human intervention
and so once you get these automatic
labels now you can sort of go ahead and
train your model with these labels the
other way of thinking about self
supervised learning is that it's really
a prediction problem where you are
trying to predict a part of the data
from the other parts of the data so you
have some observed data and you have
some hidden data and you can now
formulate a task where given the
observed data you try to predict either
the hidden data or some property of the
hidden data and so pretty much a lot of
sort of the cell supervised techniques
can be viewed in this particular
framework
so the term sort of self supervisor
thing I really like to give this analogy
which is from Virginia Tessa
so where she sort of tries to
distinguish between the three terms
supervised unsupervised and self
supervised and so supervised learning
you have say an input cow and you're
given the exact target for it which is
say going to be the label cow and
unsupervised learning you're given this
input and it's not clear what really the
entire target is what exactly is the
objective function or so on cell
supervised learning is sort of the term
which is preferred now more and more and
the idea is that the label really comes
from either a co-occurring mortality or
co-occurring part of the data itself so
really all of the power is in the data
and you're really trying to predict sort
of predict either parts of it are
properties of the data so some very sort
of standard and successful examples of
this are safe either the word to that
model they're given this say a sentence
for example the cat sits on the mat you
are given a part of the sentence that
you observe so which is in this case
labeled as the context or the history
and then you have a part of the sentence
of word in this case which is not
observed which you sort of hide from
this entire model and given this context
you ask the model to predict this target
and so you have yourself supervisor
objective you can minimize it in a
particular fashion and now you will
learn a representation for your input
data and word to back has been I mean it
has actually shown a lot of promise in
the riot II of applications and this
entire sort of predictive model has
inspired a lot of work in computer
vision as well the success of Cell
supervisor thing is sort of undebatable
in natural language processing so in
2018 there was this really successful
model called pert which basically is a
form of a mast or two encoder and this
modular sort of revolutionized the
amount of things that you can do in NLP
with limited amount of data and a lot of
people call this the image net moment of
energy
so in this talk we'll sort of again to
motivate why we want to use self
supervised learning we are really going
to focus on sort of how you can look at
data and you can use observations and
interactions of the data to formulate
self supervised tasks how you can
leverage multiple modalities and I'll
talk a little bit more about what this
term modalities means or structure in
the data to sort of learn
representations so let's move on to the
context of computer vision and I'll sort
of now try to define things that I've
been talking about in a slightly high
level in more concrete fashion first
question so cell supervised learning is
basically just unsupervised learning
right yes I mean yes yes I mean
basically the sort of main differences
like unsupervised is sort of very poorly
defined term so there is supervised but
what is unsupervised so for example the
analogy given by Jeetendra malloc is
there is a cat but there is no category
called on cat so that's the reason to
sort of come like
refer this term more and more that it's
really about using the data or the
properties of the data itself to come up
with supervision so that's why self
super so for my so Jason is a subset yes
I guess yes I mean I guess you know my
reason for Konya this is that the
algorithms the algorithms are
essentially the same as supervised
learning algorithms with some
modification as because you're kind of
training the system to learn part of its
input from another part of the input so
it's very similar to supervised many
many ways except that you need to handle
uncertainty better and the negative
category if you want may be much larger
which is kind of an issue but
unsupervised running is really not very
well defined so surprise running is kind
of a very different concept it's not
entirely clear it's a subset of
unsupervised
so moving ahead and now sort of try to
talk about self supervised learning more
in the context of vision so envision a
lot of these sort of prediction problems
have been framed as pretext tasks so lot
of the vision algorithms sort of and
this term comes more from 2015 where
from this particular paper by Carl Tosh
and the idea here was that you have a
text task or the sort of task that you
really care about at the end like image
classification but of course you don't
have a lot of data for that or you so
you want to solve a task before going to
the real task so a pretext task so this
pretext task is a prediction task that
you are solving but it's not often the
real task that you really care about so
you solve this particular task to learn
a representation and then you finally
get your downstream tasks where you want
to use this representation to perform
something meaningful
so these pretext tasks are sort of funny
they're often fairly like people got
very creative with sort of coming up
with these pretext asks so let's look at
how you can define a bunch of three text
tasks and what each of these pretext
tasks is trying to do and so you can use
either images video video and sound when
you're trying to do these things and in
each case you'll have a bunch of observe
data and you'll try to either predict
hidden data or you try to predict a
property of type in beta and this sort
of distinguishes a bunch of approaches
so let's look at how you can use images
to define something like a pretext task
so the paper that introduced this term
pretext task came up with this a fairly
sort of funny method but what you do is
you take say two image patches basically
take the network and you ask a network
to predict what is the relative position
of each patch with respect to the other
so in this case say I first sample a
blue patch and now I sample another
Dutch so what I do is I basically feed
forward both of these patches through a
cornet and I have a classifier that is
going to solve the a2 a classification
problem and how do I get the label for
this classification problem well I just
look at where the red patch is located
with respect to the blue patch and
that's it so at the end of it you're
just predicting you're just solving an
eight-way classification task
you got your labels by basically doing
this sort of exploiting this property of
the input data and that's it now you you
can use this to basically train and this
entire con that
sort of to sort of look at it in a
different way it's only solving a very
small classification problem
it's just solving basically eight
possible locations sort of a problem
surprisingly enough doing this sort of
pretext task actually learns something
fairly reasonable so the one way to look
at what this network has learned is to
look at what it considers our nearest
neighbors in its face with
representation so to explain this plot a
little bit more on the left-hand side
you have the input patch so you feed
forward this input patch through that
CNN and you basically extract a bunch of
patches on the data on your data set so
in this case imagine it and you compute
feature representations for each of
these patches now for the particular
input patch that you sent through the
content you compute the nearest
neighbors of all the patches from the
data set and you can use three different
networks to compute the feature
representations so the first column is
the relative positioning free text task
and the second column is basically a
randomly initialized Alex net and then
the third case is third column is
basically an image net pre-trained Alex
net so if you sort of look at what this
relative positioning task is capturing
it's really able to find very good
patches patches that are identical or
very close to the input patch and you
also see that it's for example like in
the row of the cat so that's the fourth
row you can see that it's actually able
to figure out it's slightly invariant to
say the colors so the input carrot was
black and white but it's actually able
to pick out cats which are not just
black and white so it's really doing
something it's trying it's at least able
to reason about patches as a whole so
why should this representation do
anything which is semantic so the
nearest neighbor visualization technique
is good at telling you what this
representation space has captured so in
this case what we can confidently say is
that this relative patch representation
has learned to sort of associate a bunch
of these local patches together local
patches that have roughly the same
appearance
and so because it is able to reason
about these local patches maybe it's
actually able to reason about an image
because image can sort of be viewed as a
bunch of local patches together so it's
able to sort of put these patches in one
part of the representation space
the now people have like I said people
have gotten fairly creative with the
kinds of pretext tasks they do so
another sort of popular pretext task is
predicting rotations of an image and
this so this task is very
straightforward you have an image you
can either apply a rotation of 0 degrees
90 degrees 180 degrees or 270 degrees to
it and basically you send in that
particular image after applying a
rotation and you ask the network to
predict what was the exact rotation
applied to the image and it just solves
a four-way classification problem so it
predicts basically either if the
rotation is 0 90 180 or 270 and this 3
text task is actually one of the most
popular pretext tasks now because it's
so easy to implement you basically just
take an image it's very very simple you
don't really need to sample too many
patches or solve any sort of complicated
thing it's a very standard architecture
and you can solve this let's become
fairly popular now so the network is
going to be basically trained so the
feature are trained in order to solve
this problem right so the output will be
somehow dependent on the specific task
someone is going to be peaking somehow
right yes so this is again this is a
pretext task so we are not really
interested in predicting the rotations
of an image we are just using this task
as a proxy to learn some features so
that on the downstream tasks say when
someone gives us a thousand labels
images of a cat we can then use this pre
trained feature representation to do
that particular task
so these pretext tests are often really
not going to make a lot of semantic
sense and that's problem like that sort
of the reason for calling them pretext
because you have a downstream task where
you actually have some semantics or some
label that you actually know is good
Thanks why would the predicting
rotations give us any sort of useful
representations yes so in fact when this
paper came out this was the question of
many many people and it was my question
as well
empirically this actually works really
and sort of my intuition for this has
basically been that in order to predict
what sort of the rotation of an object
is it needs to it roughly understand
what the boundaries or what sort of some
concepts in this image are for example
to predict that this particular image is
rotated by 180 degrees it needs to at
least recognize a sort of segregate the
sky from like the sand or the sky from
the water or at least understand that
for a tree the leaves are generally not
below sort of the bar trees don't go
grow like downwards they grow upwards so
it sort of needs to reason about some
things implicitly it's not super clear
what it really needs to do but this task
empirically works very well has then
only been tried or works as a task with
like a discrete classification or has it
has been tried on like a continuous
scale of angles at which the image is
rotated
yes so you can do both versions so you
can I mean you can sort of increase the
number of Bin's you want and as you
basically make it very very large
approaching more of a regression problem
where you have a continuous variable in
practice these four sort of angles were
pretty well increasing and there is a
question about the previous slide how
does the nearest neighborhood work in
this context do you run every patch each
patch through the CNN yes so this is
just for visualization this is just for
sort of understanding so it although it
is like sort of expensive to compute
this it gives you a very good idea of
what the representation has learned so
what the authors did was basically
extract a bunch of patches from each
image for roughly ten to nine patches
and so on a small set of images so I
think in this case it was they
fifty two hundred thousand images and
then you basically just compute nearest
neighbors on those those patches of
those images
you
that's good so another task which is
also very popular is called colorization
so in this case given a grayscale image
you basically try to predict the colors
of that image so you can really
formulate this task for any image you
can take an image you can remove its
color and you can ask a network to
basically predict the color from this
black and white or sort of grayscale
image and this task by itself is not as
it's actually useful in some respect so
a lot of like old movies when you sort
of see them colorized select movies
short and say the 40s or 30s when there
was not a lot of color technology you
can actually have this task really sort
of be applied there so in some way it
actually is more useful than other
pretext tasks and why does this task
learn something meaningful well it needs
to sort of recognize that trees are
green it needs to understand what sort
of object categories it is in order to
color it sadly well and so in practice
this has now sort of been extended to
the video domain and there are a lot of
follow-up works on sort of polarization
itself if interesting because I think
the colour mapping is not that it's not
deterministic right I mean not a mistake
yes so several several there are several
possible true solutions right yes so so
the initial paper was basically sort of
proposing a deterministic mapping so you
were solving either a classification or
the regression problem so you only could
have say a blue colored umbrella and you
could never sort of predict a gray color
and so what ended up happening was for a
lot of categories which have different
kinds of colors so for example let's
assume say you have a ball and that ball
can appear either in the red blue or
green colors the netbook would sort of
predict that to be great because I mean
that sort of the mean of all of these
things so that's the best it can do
there was follow-up work from David
Foresight's group in UIUC which tried to
sort of come up with variational
auto-encoders so you actually had a
latent variable
would have diverse colorization so in
practice you can basically do approaches
like that so you can actually have now a
green colored ball and because you're
doing that for the entire scene you can
actually have consistent colorings of
the entire scene yeah yeah that's what I
think we will be we've been talking with
yarn or whenever we have like some
mapping that goes from one to many and
then we should choose like a little
variable model which allow us to choose
a multiple solution given that we have
the same input so if I think the reason
why like people did not really focus on
a lot on that particular aspect in this
case was at least back in the day one it
was not here what was working and what
was not and second this was still a
pretext task and people were not really
concerned about the colorization quality
people were more concerned about
representation quality but I think now a
lot of us understand that both of them
are fairly sort of tied to one another
that you really need to have this sort
of non-deterministic mapping to get
something more out of the data scene
thanks and finally so this is an
apologize for this picture it's from the
paper I think it was the resolution but
so this is another task which is like
context auto-encoders so the idea is
basically borrowed pretty much from say
board to back so you hide a particular
part of the image and now given the
surrounding part of the image you need
to predict what was hidden so it's
really sort of the fill in the blanks
task
and why should this work well it's at
least trying to reason about what
objects are present so cars can run on
roads or like buildings are basically
consist consists of like windows and
closer to the ground they're supposed to
have doors and so on so it needs to
learn something more about like the
implicit structure of the data by
performing this task so this was just
about images and now I'll sort of talk
about what are the other tasks that you
can do in video so in video the sort of
main source of supervision is this
notion of sequential 'ti of frames so
frames basically have an inherent order
in them and you want to sort of use that
order to get something for example say
predict the order of frames or fill in
the blanks and a bunch of sort of other
pretext tasks that are all dependent on
sequential nature
so here I'll sort of talk about one of
the works that I did in 2016 which was
about predicting the temporally correct
or incorrect order of frames this is
very much inspired from earlier that
yawn and basically others stayed on sort
of sequential ordering of frames through
contrast of the thing and I'll talk
about those towards the end when I
actually talk about contrast observing
so in this particular work we were very
much inspired by like the pretext asks
again and we saw the binary
classification problem so given a bunch
of frames we extract three frames and if
we extract them in the right order we
label them plus one and if we shuffle
them basically we label them as zero and
so now we need to solve a binary
classification problem to predict
whether something is shuffled or not
and the reason this sort of works is
because so given three frames or let's
think of them as basically start middle
and end this network really tries to
learn given a start and end point is
this point of valid sort of
interpolation of the start and end
points so it really tries to sort of
interpolate smoothly these features
given these given this visual input so
the network is fairly straightforward
it's a sort of triplets Iommi's network
you have three frames you feed forward
each one of them independently you
concatenate the features that you obtain
from these three frames and the new
perform a binary classification problem
so you predict whether this thing is
correct or incorrect
whether it's basically a shuffle does
not shuffled you get up you can
basically minimize this with
cross-entropy loss and you can train
this entire network end-to-end
so again like I had mentioned earlier
nearest neighbor is sort of a good way
to visualize what these networks are
learning so we further player work can
be basically looked at the nearest
neighbors of frames so on the left hand
side you have a query frame and you feed
forward that frame you get a feature and
then you basically look at the nearest
neighbors in that feature representation
so we will do that for image net shuffle
and learn and then random features so
what you observe is there's sort of sort
of very stark difference between what
image net shuffle and random give you so
the first row if you look at the sort of
gym scene emission it is really good at
figuring out that it's a gym scene it's
the nearest neighbor it retrieves looks
is very different from the initial scene
that we like the initial image that
we've given so like the floor is much
better late in the query the floor was
actually black and the exact exercise
being performed is not really the same
but imagenet is sort of really good at
collapsing this entire semantic category
and really sort of bringing in various
different gem scenes together close by
in the representation space the same
thing sort of goes for the row below
so can you have an outdoor scene and
emission it is immediately able to sort
of pick up on that outdoor part of it
it's able to figure out there is grass
and so on and it sort of brings these
two points together in the feature space
if you look at say the sort of rightmost
the nearest neighbors retrieve by the
random network you see that it really
focuses on the color so in the top row
it's a sort of focusing on the black
floor it's really looking at maybe it's
sort of the black color in this image
and that's how it's written against
nearest neighbor now if you look at the
shuffle and learn the nearest neighbors
they're fairly odd it's not immediately
clear whether it's focusing on the color
or whether it's focusing on that entire
semantic concept and so on sort of
further inspection and after looking at
a lot of these examples we figured out
that it was really looking at the pose
of the person so if you look at in the
top row the person is doing sort of an
upset is upside down and that's sort of
the nearest neighbor retrieved as well
and in the second row also the person is
sort of has their foot and of like has a
feet in the particular way and it's
really trying to sort of get there with
its nearest neighbor and it's sort of
ignoring the entire stream it's not
really focused on the background
and when we were thinking about this why
would a netbook even try to do something
of this sort well we looked we thought
back to our pretext asked so the pretext
asked was predicting the order or
basically predicting whether things are
in the right order or not and to do this
you really need to focus on what is
moving in the same or sort of the in
this case the people so if you focus on
the background you will never be able to
answer this question
fare thee well because well the
background doesn't change a lot between
three frames that had taken sort of
close by in a video the only thing that
sort of changes is the person or the
sort of things that are moving in that
video so sort of accidentally we
basically trained a network that was
really trying to sort of look at things
that are moving and then ended up
focusing on the pose of this pose of
people now of course this is my
interpretation we wanted to verify this
quantitatively so what we did is we took
our representation and we fine-tuned it
on this task of human key point
estimation so this task is basically
given up human you need to sort of
predict where certain key points are so
the key points are going to keep they're
defined as basically say the nose the
neck the left shoulder right shoulder
right elbow left elbow wrist and so on
so you basically have these bunch of
predefined key points and you train the
network to sort of predict this so this
is really useful for something like
tracking or pose estimation of a person
so we took our shuffle and learn self
supervised method and we fine-tuned it
on these two data sets called flick and
n PII and we did the same thing for a
mission and supervised network and this
is back in the days of Alex Nets so Alex
net was the architecture that we used
and in sort of fairly surprisingly what
we found is that the self supervised
representation was very competitive or
even slightly better than imagining
supervised representation at this task
of key point estimation so in this case
what I'm measuring is a you see which is
area under the curve so higher is better
and you can see that it's performing
fairly
which was very surprising to us because
we hadn't any thought about this task
when we were designing a pretext RSP
really thought that I think this pretext
task will help us understand actions
better but it turns out that if like you
you can have sort of surprising outcomes
depending on what you ended up or what
you end up creating as a pretext task so
in this case that was both estimation so
for this example
you said you fine-tuned it on human key
point estimation so is that kind of like
a supervised step like once you have
your yes pretext representations yes so
so the pipeline basically generally goes
like you have you do a pre training step
so that can basically be say supervision
which is predicting one of thousand
classes and then you have a downstream
task where you have a few amount of
labels so you basically just so in this
case that's predicting the human key
points so the this way of evaluation
what it does is it basically has it
takes a bunch of three trained networks
and then it fine gives them using the
same supervised data at the end and so
what you're evaluating is how good was
it if I started from say a mission and
supervised network or a shuffle and
learn network to perform this task of
key point estimation okay thank you
change that this well since shuffle and
all focuses on the background so it
actually focuses a lot on the four count
so that's what I was trying to sort of
come up with this talk about in this
example if you look at like what the
nearest neighbor that is really looking
at the person to come up with this right
it's looking at the upside-down person
to sort of come up with its nearest
neighborhood and the reason is if you
want to talk about ordering of frames
actually need to focus on things that
move and in these videos people are the
things that move so if it focuses on the
background it actually will not be able
to solve the shuffle and learn tasks
you
all right so this was sort of surprising
and it sort of goes to show that if you
design your pretext ask well it will
work well for a certain sort of set of
downstream tasks and there have been
sort of fairly nice methods since then
which have been basically about
predicting this sort of using
sequentiality and sort of predicting
whether things are in the correct order
or not so this is odd without networks
which basically rather than solving a
binary classification problem it
actually tries to predict which which of
the frames is the unlike sort of the one
that is odd one out the one that is sort
of a shuffled and this because you're
sort of increasing the amount of
information that you're predicting at
the output this sort of network ends up
doing better and better and it also sort
of reasons about more frames at a time
so now you've seen sort of images and
video there's been a lot of creative
work at the sort of multimodal so where
you have to sip modalities video and
sound or to sensory inputs and these two
have been sort of very popular and very
nice sort of work coming out of this
regime so the key sort of signaling in
these works is predicting whether an
image or say a video clip corresponds to
an audio clip so the way you can sort of
construct these tasks is to take a video
and you can basically just sample any
frame from it and this similarly take an
audio track and sample any part of that
and now the problem is basically to
predict whether these things are
corresponding or not so essentially
in this entire sort of video surfer drum
you can sample the frame and the
corresponding audio and call that the
positive and in this case you basically
take a different video and you take the
audio from the drum video and that
becomes your negative and so again you
can solve a binary classification
problem by taking these bunch of
positives and negatives
so the architecture for this is fairly
straightforward
you take in an image you pass it through
a vision sub Network now you have your
audio you pass it through an audio sub
Network and get 128 dimensional features
for them so also embeddings then you
sort of fuse them together and have a
binary classification problem saying
whether these things correspond or not
so at the end of it is just solving a
single binary problem what it sort of
shows is that it you can actually do a
bunch of sort of nice things when you
train that works this way so you can
answer the question what is making a
sound because the network really needs
to focus on say to predict whether the
sound is coming from this video it also
needs to identify what in the video
might be making the sound so if it's the
sound of a guitar it needs to sort of
understand what our guitars roughly
looks like or if it's a drum it sort of
things to roughly identify were two
drummers so in this particular case the
author sort of looked at visualizations
for in this case two instruments so you
have a piano and a flute and you look at
just the radio information and nothing
else the network autumn already sort of
puts a very high sort of visual
importance on the piano and on the flute
and this is because it autumn when you
sort of feed forward this image it knows
that there are going to be these two
kinds of things that can produce sounds
so it really sort of learns to identify
these kinds of objects automatically
you know about the the slide before
whenever you had the convolutional net
over the space program do you know what
is the kernel size for that audio
content just I'm interested to know like
whether it makes sense to have like
rectangular or a square kernel size I
mean now there are sort of modem proof
models so this is basically operating on
the log spec program so yeah it is still
handcraft you need to decide how your
computing that spectrogram exactly
people have now figured out that you can
actually use the raw audio and you can
actually apply cons directly on the
audio signal yeah yeah sure sure and for
that it's generally a small window it
really depends on what the corresponding
video that you're using so roughly about
a seconds worth of audio in a second
worth of video so now that I've sort of
shown you how there are like multiple
different creative ways of defining what
a pretext ask is let's try to see what a
pretext ask learns and how can you sort
of if the if I give you 25 different
pretext asks how can you a priori decide
which one is the one that you want to
use and what are they going to sort of
learn so the first thing is pretext asks
are actually complementary so there was
this really nice paper in 2017 that
looked at two of these sort of tasks so
relative position was the first pretext
asked I talked about where you take two
patches and you try to predict what
their relative position with respect to
one another is and colorization is
basically taking a grayscale image and
trying to predict its colors and so what
these authors showed is basically that
if you train a single network to do both
of these tasks to predict both the
colorize colorize output as well as
relative position you can actually get
gains in performance so again this is
evaluated the same way I was talking
about earlier you have a pre area
network
then you're basically evaluating it on
an end task in this case imagenet
classification and detection benchmark
and in both cases you sort of can get
gains by performing both of these tasks
so you get best of both words so in some
way what this also shows you is that a
single pretext task may not be the right
answer so predicting just coloured or
predicting just relative position may
not be the right answer to learn cell
supervised representations in fact if
you sort of reason about what
information is being predicted it really
varies a lot across tasks so starting
with the relative position task you're
predicting a fairly low level
information you're predicting just sort
of eight possible locations so just to a
to a classification problem or for that
shuffle unknown problem you're
predicting whether things are shuffled
or not so it's just a simple binary
problem so it's very sort of less amount
of information that's being predicted
whereas if you look at on the extreme
right if you are trying to predict what
is missing in an image and you're trying
to reconstruct the pixels you're
predicting all sort of information
because that entire box contains I mean
it can have a very you can have a very
different appearance space right so if
you have in pixels then you can
basically have a lot of different values
for that entire predictive region so
you're predicting a lot of information
there so essentially this is one simple
way of thinking about pretext asks how
much information are you predicting and
that can give you already a good idea of
you know whether you're actually
predicting a lot of information so
probably that representation is actually
going to be better so in general this is
sort of going to guide the next part of
my talk you can think of this sort of
predicting more information part as on
an axis and I'll talk about three
different sort of categories and this
actually two different categories so
pretext asks is what I've been talking
about till now which is just predicting
simple classification problems like
different degrees of rotation or so on I
sort of move to contrastive methods
which are which actually predict say
more information than these pretext
tasks and in this particular talk I'm
actually not going to talk about
generative models but interactive models
predict more information than say a
typical contrastive method and so this
is basically one way of thinking about
these classes of methods question how do
we train multiple training pre training
tasks do we shuffle data for both tasks
it's training dividual you want it lead
to catastrophic forget in right so the
simple way of doing that is basically
that you have so you can basically
alternate batches so you can have the
same network and in one batch you
basically feed it black-and-white images
and you ask it to predict the colored
part of it and in the second now in the
second batch you basically feed it
patches and you ask it to do the
relative position tasks you basically
have two different like head like fully
connected layers at the top so you can
basically alternate between these tasks
what the authors of the paper did was
actually slightly more sophisticated
they had they basically had sort of
multi task network which was three or
four depending on the number of pretext
tasks you have and you actually solve
all of them at once but they there was
sort of more involved weight sharing
across these four three four different
task networks hi so about the pretest
asks what performance should be aimed
for in a pretext ask when do we know
that this is enough or when can we stop
and because ultimately we care about the
performance on the downstream that's
question one and question two is you
were speaking about low information and
more information for example in the case
where you mentioned where you were
predicting whether it's in the correct
sequence or not you could have also
predicted the actual permutation of the
images right so how do you decide
between which task to follow and based
on work so both parts the second part of
the question actually that's going to be
in a couple of slides I'll sort of defer
to that question or that one later but
the first part how much do you train
this model on a
texts asked so a sort of good sign of a
pretext asked is that as your accuracy
on the pretext asked improves so as you
get better at predicting whether things
are shuffled or not or as you get better
at predicting rotations the sort of
accuracy on the downstream semantic
tasks will also improve so a good rule
of thumb for is basically using these
pretext tasks is we sort of have a very
difficult pretext ask or try to make it
as difficult as possible and then sort
of optimize or like reduce the loss on
that pretext task so so that your final
downstream accuracy improves so it's
very correlated
right so in practice you'll actually
drain the entire pipeline each line each
time like the pretext and the downstream
and measure the performance and rise so
it's not like you stop the pretext at a
certain point and then switch over to
only like downstream or something so
that's um generally how these methods
are evaluated but I guess when you're
developing you probably do this pipeline
multiple times
so these methods are sort of trained
like you do you're pretext ask then you
stop and then you perform your
downstream evolution task and that gives
you the final sort of measurement of how
good your pretext asked was and that's
it you do do this entire thing once
right thank you
the second part of your question the
mode information part I'll sort of come
to it later the permutation and so on
good so these are sort of the three main
buckets and the first two were what are
going to be covered basically now so
this was another word peep did which was
basically about scaling self supervised
learning so in this particular work we
focused on two problems one was the
colorization problem that I had talked
about earlier and the second is this
more sort of in film or information
variant of the relative position task so
this task is called jigsaw puzzles the
idea is that you take an image and you
split it into multiple different patches
and you try to predict exactly and even
if shuffle these patches basically by a
permutation and then you predict which
permutation was applied to the input so
that's very similar to what Chris was
suggesting here
alright so the way you solve this
problem is you take say in this case
three patches you feed forward each one
of these patches independently you
concatenate their feature and then you
classify which permutation was basically
used to permute these input patches now
the authors used nine patches to solve
this problem and that's basically going
to be nine factorial which is like 360
thousand number of permutations of
course when you're trying to perform
this classification at the end this
means that you're fully connected layer
should have 360 thousand output neurons
which is a very large number so in
practice what the authors did was
basically have a sort of a subset of
permutations that they use so say they
sample one hundred permutations from the
nine factorial permutations and then
just have this perform this hundred
weight classification right so in some
way you can look at this the size of
this subset as the problem complexity or
the amount of information that you're
predicting if you predict the full nine
factorial thing you're actually solving
that you'd basically predicting a lot of
information at the output if you only
subsample say two or three permutations
and you're basically not predicting a
lot of information so the problem
basically gets harder and harder as the
size of the subset increases so in this
paper we basically wanted to study this
the entire role of how much information
that you predict and how good is the
final representation that you learn so
in terms of evaluation there are two
ways to sort of evaluate once you have a
self supervised pretend network and this
is a lot of debate on which one is
exactly the right method to evaluate
networks so the first way is to
basically fine-tune all the layers of a
network so that you have a downstream
tasks a pose estimation or say image
classification you train this network
can you update all the parameters of
this network for the downstream tasks
the second way is to just use your
network as a feature extractor so you
basically run your images through it you
get your feature representation and now
you only train a linear classifier on
top of that fixed feature representation
so in this but
we said that a good representation
should transfer with little amount of
training so we opted basically for the
second part which is just to train a
linear classifier on top of a network
treated as a feature extractor so there
are of course different pros and cons of
using both methods so the first method
that is fine tuning all the layers is
treating the cell supervised network as
an initialization because you're
basically updating the entire network so
if your downstream tasks basically has
say 1 million images your base updating
your entire network for that 1 million
images whereas in the second case you're
just training very limited number of
parameters on the feeds fixed feature
extractor so in some way basically the
second one is measuring how good of a
feature is that that you've done
all right so the other thing that is
sort of critical in evaluating self
supervised methods is to evaluate them
on a bunch of different tasks so earlier
when I talked about that shuffle and
learn work I just showed you results in
pose estimation so on pose estimation it
was doing really there but I actually
did not do really well on other tasks
like say action recognition so in this
particular evaluation we sort of wanted
to correct that mistake and we wanted to
focus on multiple different tasks so a
variety of different tasks like say
image classification you short learning
object detection 3d understanding
navigation and so on so we defined
basically like a set of nine different
tasks so the way to evaluate the
representations is basically to extract
fixed features and you can extract these
fixed features from different parts of
the network so they can come basically
from a layer which is very close to the
input or from a very high-level layer
which is very close to the output so in
this way you sort of measuring the
semantic Ness of each of these different
layers
and the sort of standard thing we did
floor a lot of these experiments was to
use an image classification task to sort
of understand what is going on so the
image classification task is on this
data set called the EOC which is fairly
standard for detection and
classification and the idea is to
predict whether an image has one of
twenty classes so and an image can
actually have more than one class for
example like that picture of a person
with a dog that has both person and dog
so this network now needs to recognize
both the objects in it so it's not
slightly harder than image net where you
basically need to only certified n25 one
of the key objects in the image
so so the first thing we did was
basically to verify the hypothesis
whether increasing the amount of
information predicted actually results
in better representations so on the
x-axis and we are increasing the number
of permutations that we are using to
basically train our network so that's
going from 100 to 10,000 and on the
y-axis we are basically measuring the
downstream transferred performance of
these pre-trained representations and
it's measured using a metric called map
which is mean average precision so
essentially because this is a fairly
this is a sort of multi-label
classification problem you're going to
measure average precision for each of
the different 20 classes and then you're
going to compute the mean of that of
this precision so higher is better in
this case so we do that for two
different architectures Aleks net what
was originally used in the jigsaw paper
and then the resonate 50 and what you
observe is for Alex net increasing the
amount of permutations is useful up to a
certain point but the gain is overall
limited whereas for ResNet if you
increase the amount of permutations the
representation quality gets better and
better and our hypothesis was basically
that the resonant model has enough
capacity that it can actually solve a
very difficult permutation problem and
when it solves a difficult permutation
problem it's able to sort of learn much
better representations that generalize
to different downstream tasks so the
next thing we did was to evaluate our
method on the object detection task so
object detection is basically where you
try to identify what objects are present
in an image we try to draw a box around
them and your measured basically based
on how sort of good the boxes around the
object and whether you were able to
identify all the objects in an image and
again for this one we use the same vo C
beta set
so this was the setting where we
basically fine-tuned all the layers of a
network because that's what standard in
detection and what we observed was
basically on two different splits of
this video see data set the jigsaw
method was actually fairly comparable
within the margin of error to basically
training a emission supervised method so
you have a emission supervised Network
you find you in that on the task of
detection and you get a mean average
precision of 70 point five or seventy
six point two and the jigsaw method is
basically within the margin of error of
these methods which in itself sort of
shows that it actually had some sort of
nice semantic property and it was able
to localize objects a level and to put
this sort of in context for semantic
feature learning on like in computer
vision especially object detection is
sort of considered the benchmark data
set to to reach something like really
belong and this result basically when
we've sort of published it was the
closest anyone had ever come to
supervise free training in terms of
detection
right it's some question um so is
TechStars
similar to what we could try achieving
with transfer learning is it like a
subset of that or yes so I mean the way
you evaluate these pretext tasks is by
transfer learning so you perform your
original pretext tasks and then you find
unit on a data set for a particular task
like detection so the evaluation is
always transfer learning
so the next task we looked at was
surface normal evaluation so this is
basically given input you try to
estimate what are the 3d properties of
the like basically at each pixel
location in the input you try to predict
what is the surface orientation so in 3d
basically the XY & z vectors at each
particular surface so it's a sort of
dense prediction problem where you need
to assign that XYZ vector to each
location in the input and for that to
use this nice dataset created by N by U
and we basically measured the prediction
properties of our method with risk and
compared it to an image net supervised
method and so in this case we measured
the median error and the percentage
correct predictions so the median error
basically means that lower is better and
percentage correct means higher is
better so it turned out that the jigsaw
pre-training task was actually really
good in this case and it provided like
significant improvements over a
missionary training so it was basically
across some multiple different sets
multiple different splits it was able to
really easily outperform the image net
supervised Praetorian method so again it
sort of goes on to show that evaluating
a pretext task on multiple different
tasks and multiple different data sets
is really important to understand what
is really going on in a pretext task so
somehow jigsaw is really incorporating
something about like geometry and
something about like pixel level
information much better than image net
supervised methods
so finally we found sort of the Achilles
heel of this method like the tics of
returning tasks so to do this we
evaluated on like the setting called few
short loading so in few short loading
you have very sort of limited number of
training examples and you are training
your classifier just on these very
limited number of training examples so
on the x-axis I have the number of
training examples that were used to
train a method so that goes from say 1
to 96 and I'm sort of showing you curves
for for like ourselves like 2 different
cell supervised methods so jigsaw
methods trained on two different data
sets imagenet which is on the top and a
random has next 50 so what you can
observe is that there is a significant
gap in performance between a Cell
supervised method and a supervised
method and that gap basically just does
not seem to reduce as you increase the
number of labeled examples which point
which sort of shows that cell supervised
representations although they may be
good at tasks like say pose estimation
or particular tasks like surface normal
estimation there is still a lot of
difference between what sort of semantic
aspect of the data they captured because
this in this sort of few short learning
tasks if I give you one image and if
you're able to say something about it
your feature representation needs to be
really good to solve that task
the other lady evaluated this method was
to basically look at what it learns at
each different layer so we basically
trained linear classifiers on different
like different clear representations in
a ResNet 50 so from the con one which is
going to be the layer closest to the
input to the output say of there is two
block there is three block and there is
five block so this five is basically the
sort of highest level representation
that you get out from resonate 50 and
after that representation is where you
perform this entire jigsaw like
predicting the permutation task and so
you look at in this case the x-axis
represents the sort of where the feature
is coming from con 1 or s 5 and on the
y-axis we are looking at the again mean
after position of image classification
on GOC and funnily enough what you see
is basically that the representation
quality improves when you go from corn 1
to s 4 so it steadily in sort of
increases in the mean average precision
but towards the end there's a sharp drop
so restful to res 5 is a sharp drop in
performance which is that due to the
finally specializes to the specific task
yes exactly so this was very worrying
because if you were to sort of plot this
thing for a supervised Network you
observe that from convent to rs5 the
representation quality always improves
and this is true for like pretty much
any good supervised network whereas for
a lot of the self supervised networks we
sort of repeated this experiment for the
rotation network but colorization for
relative position he would always
observe this very sharp gap in from
Brest fortress 5 and so this says that
the end task that we are solving the
pretext asked is probably not very nice
because it's not very well aligned to
the downstream semantic tasks that we
really want to solve
which basically brings me to the next
part which is to understand what is
missing from these pretext are these
sort of proxy tasks
so recap pretext tasks are basically
something like predicting rotation or to
predict say jigsaw puzzles and it's very
sort of if you look at it in the bigger
picture of things they're very
surprising and the fact that they even
work is super surprising
so for pretext tasks we have this
pre-training step where which is
supervised and then we have our transfer
tasks which are imaged classification or
detection and it's really a lot of
wishful thinking and a lot of hope that
the pre-training task and the transfer
task are super aligned and there is no
evidence really it's a lot of just like
wishing really really hard that whatever
pretext ask we've come up with this
really better line with our transfer
task and solving that p-tex task will do
really well in transfer tasks so what of
research basically goes into designing
these pretext tasks and implementing
them really well but it's not clear why
solving something like jigsaw puzzles
should teach us anything about semantics
or for example even the case of say beat
supervisor thing where you are trying to
predict hashtags from an image it's not
clear by predicting hashtags of an image
is actually going to do something well
for learning some like a good classifier
on transfer tasks so this question
remains that how do you design good pre
training tasks which are well aligned
with your transfer tasks so this hope of
generalization is basically you can and
the way we can sort of evaluate this is
basically by looking at the
representation that each layer and if
the last clear we do not see
representations that are well aligned
with the transfer task then that is a
red flag in that sort of telling us that
maybe this retaining task is not really
the right task to solve
so like I mentioned earlier this
basically is the sort of pattern that we
get for jigsaw and this shows us that
probably the last layers are very much
specialized towards that Excel problem
right so in general what we really want
from pre-trained features is that they
should represent how images are related
to one another so feature representation
stood and this basically goes back to
say the nearest neighbor visualizations
that I had it should really be able to
group together images that are
semantically related in some way and the
second property is basically a property
that has been the backbone of designing
vision features so even before sale the
deep learning features were popular the
handcrafted features were always all
about invariance about sort of being
invariant to things like lighting or
things like exact color or exact
location so these are the two properties
that we really want in that retain
features and there are sort of two ways
of achieving these things one is
clustering and the other is contrast
observing and both these methods have
promised because they are really solving
that basically trying to get these
properties when they're sort of trying
to learn representations and I believe
that's why they've actually now started
performing so much better than whatever
pretext asks that were hand designed for
so far so now I sort of focus on two
recent works that we have which are
which fall into this pocket of
clustering and invariances so one is
called plus surfeit the other is called
purl and both of them will be presented
at CVG artists yeah so the first work is
classified it's a method which we think
is very good to improve generalization
of visual representations so the
clustering is basically a good way to
understand what images are grouped
together what images go together and
whatever it is do not go together and
it's sort of dip you by basically
performing clustering on the feature
space you can get these nice buckets of
images that are related and images that
are not related so the main idea of this
paper is extremely simple there are just
two steps one is the cost of step the
other is the predict step so what we do
is we take any up
network and this can be any preacher a
net worth it it does not really have to
be just a self supervised network it can
either be a imaginary train network or a
network pre-trained say using hashtags
or a cell supervised network like one
train to predict jigs or permutations
and you take this free trade network
when you extract a bunch of features
from it on a set of images and of course
these images have no labels you extract
these features when you perform k-means
clustering and what you now get is
basically for each label for each image
you know which cluster it belongs to and
that becomes its label so in the second
fit step what you do is you train a
network from scratch so like from random
bits and you train this network to
predict just these pseudo labels so if
pseudo because they were basically
obtained using clustering so they're not
really hard labels which were given by
say a human annotator
and so now this second network is just
trying to predict these cluster
assignments so it takes our image and it
tries to predict which one of the K
clusters that you got from your k-means
does this image belong to so a standard
pre train and transfer task is to
basically perform your pre training so
that's the top row is to perform your
pre training on an objective like
predicting hashtags or predicting GPS
locations and then to evaluate this
feature based by learning linear probe
in the cluster fit world we basically do
not touch the pre-training so you
perform your free training as you were
you just insert a step in between which
is the cluster fit step where you take a
dataset D and you take your praetor
Network and you learn a new network from
scratch on this data and finally you
basically use this like green network
for all your downstream tasks so the
reason we believe that this method works
is because the clustering step and then
you are sort of clustering just these
images you are only capturing the
essential information which is basically
what images go together and what images
do not go together so you read through
away all the other information that is
present in the original Network just
capturing the sort of entered image
relationships that were captured and let
that were modeled by the initial network
and to sort of understand this we
performed a fairly simple experiment we
added label noise so synthetic label
noise to imagenet and we trained a
network basically on this noisy image
net so just flip a bunch of image labels
and train a network and now you evaluate
the feature representation from this
network on a downstream task which is
again a mesh net but it's a much larger
version of image net so it's 9,000
weight classification so we basically on
the x-axis have the amount of label
noise added to the images so that's
going from 0% to 75% and on the y-axis
we are looking at the transfer
performance on the larger image net the
emission at 9,000 dataset so the pink
line is showing you the pre-trained
network which is of it and basically as
the amount of label noise increases the
pre-trained networks performance on the
downstream tasks decreases and well this
is not surprising because as your labels
become less and less reliable of course
your representation quality is going to
suffer so that sort of goes down very
quickly in the sort of blue line of the
experiment with this technique called
module desolations where you take your
initial network and you use that to
generate labels so you look at the
output of that network and you look at
the sort of confidence in the outputs
generate labels for a second network and
that's called modelled isolation so
model resolution generally performs
better than the pre trained network and
you can see that all across so as
they'll amount of label noise increases
the distillation model actually is much
better than the original and finally
towards the end we have classified so
that's the green line and you can see
that the classified model is
consistently better than basically any
of these methods either distillation or
pre-training and consistently gives
better results including when you have
zero level noise
which is basically when you have a
pre-trained imagenet network so we
applied elaborate on the difference
between distillation and clustered fit
once more yes so in yes so in
distillation what you would do is you
would basically so in this first step
you would take the pre-trained Network
and you would use the labels this
network is predicting so say the the
network basically predicts 1,000 classes
so you basically use those labels in a
software fashion to generate generate
labels for your images so say the
network was trained to predict 100
different types of dogs so you take your
images and you get a distribution over
100 different types of dogs and use that
distribution to train your second
network whereas in cluster fit you don't
really care about the label space or the
sort of output output space of the pre
trained network you only look at the
features you don't even look at the last
fully connected you just look at the
previous features got it all so why
would the software distribution help
with training like why we're training on
this be helped what's like the intuition
behind this solution relations mean
intuition is basically that if your
network was trained really well so
suppose you had no label noise this
because a lot of things are not really a
lot of images really don't belong in the
in this sort of same classes so suppose
your data set actually had hundred two
hundred different types of dogs but you
had only hundred of them labeled and so
for a lot of these images say you
actually had to assign you had to pick
basically which one of the dogs it was a
software distribution is basically going
to help you discover hidden categories
so it's basically 0.5 kind this guide
type of dog in point 5 this kind of dog
so basically having these sort of
software labels helps you enhance sort
of the initial class distribution that
you have
okay thank you so we applied this method
to the cell supervised learning so the
jigsaw task that me I talked about
earlier and we were able to see
surprising amounts of gains across a
bunch of data sets so the jigsaw method
is in the top row which and I'm in each
of those sort of columns you're looking
at the transfer performance of basically
this jigsaw method on a bunch of
different data sets if you apply cluster
fit to district saw method you actually
can see gains across all of these data
sets and they're fairly consistent and
we perform this test on a bunch of
different three training methods like
coordinate so predicting rotations and
again we could see fairly nice gains
across these four different data sets
and surprisingly enough cluster fit
really works on any pre-trained Network
so it can be either a fully supervised
Network or a weekly supervised Network
so say a network that was trained to
predict hashtags or a weekly supervised
video network or basically any cell
supervised network and in each of these
cases we can observe fairly consistent
and large gains when you have like
specific so it's actually able to
improve the generalization of most of
these methods I think you're dragging
your microphone around it's very noisy
yeah so the second thing is basically
these gains were possible without extra
data labels or changes in the
architecture so in some ways you can
think of this as being self supervised
find you next step so you have your pre
trained network and then you basically
perform this cluster step which is
classified step which is completely
supervised or unsupervised and then you
can observe that the representation
quality improves I had a question in the
in the slide that you showed the
improvement with jigsaw and
and by using classified so in this
cluster for it is it's everything right
it is not using jigsaw at all so it is
applied on top of the jigsaw method
right so there was a pretend network
from which you exact features right so
in this case that pretend network is the
tricks or pretend network oh okay
participate and network and then you
basically perform yourself it on top of
it okay I think the main sort of
intuition is that when you say perform
the jigsaw task the last layer becomes
very much fine-tuned for that particular
jigsaw task right so we saw that
accuracy go down now when you take those
features and you perform clustering on
it you can think of this as basically
you're reducing the amount of
information right here if I drain the
second network to directly regress the
features of the first network I would
basically get the same exact network but
if I drain the second network only to
predict what images are grouped together
in the first one I'm actually predicting
lesser information and I thinking is
basically that clustering is some kind
of a noise removal technique so it's
really removing all the artifacts that
are specific to jigsaw from that like
feature space and so the second network
is actually learning something slightly
more generic all right that's sort of
the reason for like this experiment as
well so in this case we sort of
empirically validate that hypothesis by
actually ingesting amount of label noise
so the last layer basically is going to
get more and more than oisi and when you
do cluster fit on top of this you
actually again see improvement so that's
sort of our validation of this
hypothesis I had another question
so did you measure the performance of
class defect on object detection like
did it perform as well or it was it just
great in classification so it performs
well in detection as well so it actually
performs well indeed yes so there were
initial experimental detection where it
actually does perform the
we did not really push a lot of the
detection aspect of it in this
particular paper people sort of more
interested in the retrieval or like
linear classification kind of
experiments okay because either thinking
is feels like making these pseudo labels
we were basically making it I'm able to
classification tasks instead of
detection task maybe we could lose one
of some of those features that jigsaw
got right that is possible at least the
initial experiments that I had run did
not seem to suggest this there was
improvement in detection it was minor
but detection improvements overall like
the gap in performance is already so
small that the improvements actually
they're generally very small in general
okay in the same cluster fit algorithm
so we'll the final layer of cluster fit
algorithm not get again covariant to the
to the labels that were used for
training it on that task it becomes less
covariant so what we found was if you
were to sort of the paper has this plot
I don't have it at the slide
unfortunately the paper has the plot
where okay this particular plot where we
were looking at con one to res 5 plus if
it is much better so there s files
through as for gap for cluster fit is
much smaller than it is for say chicks
or rotten egg but was it better than rs4
it was slightly worse so it was on on
GOC on classification it was better but
for other tasks like imagine it was
slightly worse so it did not completely
fix the problem okay which was sort of
the motivation for poll so basically
I'll not talk about well so soul was
sort of born from the hypothesis again
that you need to be invariant to please
free text tasks so before I get into the
details of poll I will talk really a
little bit about Angelica contrast of
learning how many minutes do I have by
the way 15 minutes more or less okay so
contrasted learning is basically a sort
of general framework that tries to learn
a feature space that can combine
together or sort of put together points
that are related and push apart points
that are not related so in this case
imagine like the blue boxes are the
related points the greens are the
related and the purple are the related
points you will extract features for
each of these or like each of these data
points through a shared network so which
is called a signees network you get a
bunch of image features for these each
of these data points and then you apply
a loss function which is a contrastive
loss function which is going to try to
like sort of minimize the distance
between the blue points as opposed to
say the distance between the dew point
and the green point but the distance
basically between the blue points should
be less than the distance between the
blue point and the green point or the
view point and the virtual point so
embeddings me from the related samples
should be much closer than embeddings
from the undulated samples so that's
sort of the general idea or fortress of
learning and of course yon was one of
the first teacher to sort of propose
this method and his earlier people that
I also teach is called dr. Lim and so
contrastive learning has now made a
resurgence in self supervise I think
pretty much a lord of the self
supervised state-of-the-art methods are
really based on contrasted learning and
the main question is how do you define
what is related and unrelated so in the
case of supervised learning that's
fairly clear all of the dog images are
related images all and any image that is
not a dog image is basically an
unrelated image but it's not so clear
how to define this elated and
unlimitedness
in this case of self supervised learning
the other sort of main difference from
something like a free text ask is that
contrasted birthing really reasons about
the entire or like a lot of data at once
so so go back to my previous slide this
if you look at the loss function it
always involves multiple images right it
involves
so in the first two it involves
basically the blue images and the green
images in the second row it involves the
blue images and the political images
whereas if you look at a task like say
jigsaw or a task like rotation
you're always reasoning about a single
image independently so that's sort of
another difference with contrast of
learning contrasted learning always
reason support for multiple data points
at once so now coming to the questions
how do you define related or unrelated
images you can actually use similar
techniques to what I was talking about
earlier you can use frames of a video so
you can use the sort of sequential
nature of data so to sort of understand
that frames that are nearby in a video
are related and range say from a
different video or which are further
away in time or unrelated and that sort
of has formed the basis of a lot of
supervised learning methods in this area
so if you know of this popular method
called CPC which is contrastive
predictive coding that really relies on
the sequential nature of a signal and it
basically says that samples that are
closed by in like the time space are
related and samples that are further
apart in the time space are unrelated
and it's a fairly large amount of work
basically exploiting this it can either
be in the speech the domain it can
either be in video it can be in text or
it can be in particular images and
recently we've also been working on
video and audio so basically saying this
is that a video and it's corresponding
audio are relate examples like video and
audio from a different image video are
basically underrated samples and some of
the early work in like sort of
supervised everything also use this
quadratic learning method and really
define to later examples was fairly
interesting so you run a tracker an
object tracker over a video and that
sort of gives you a point like a sort of
moving patch and what you say is that
any patch that was tracked by
cracker is related to my original patch
whereas any patch from a different video
is based is not related patch and so
that basically gives you these bunch of
related and unselected samples so if you
look at in this case Figure see where
you have this like distance notation
what this network tries to learn is
basically that patches that are coming
from the same video are related and
patches that are coming from words from
different videos are not related and so
in some bait automatically learns about
different poses of a object so a cycle
viewed from like different viewing
angles on or like different poses of a
dog and it tries to sort of group them
together so in general if you just talk
about images a lot of work is done on
looking at nearby image patches versus
distant patches so most of the sort of
CPC version one and CPC version two
methods are really a sort of exploiting
this property of images so what you do
is you have image patches that are close
by you call them as positives and image
patches that are further apart like far
farther away in the image are considered
as negatives and then you basically just
minimize a contrast if loss using this
sort of definition of positives and
negatives the more sort of popular or
like performant way of doing this is to
look at patches coming from an image and
contrast them with patches coming from a
different image so this sort of forms
the basis of a lot of popular methods
like instance discrimination moco pearl
sims here the idea is basically what's
shown in the image you sort of get into
more detail what these methods do is to
extract two completely random patches
from an image so these patches can be
overlapping they can actually become two
contained within one another or they can
be completely far apart and it then
applies some sort of data augmentation
so in this case say a color chittering
or removing the color or so on and then
you define these two patches to be your
sort of positive
examples you extract another patch from
a different image and this is again a
random patch and that basically becomes
just negative and a lot of these methods
will extract a lot of negative patches
and then they will basically perform
contrastive learning so you are relating
to positive samples but you have a sort
of negative sample that you are
contrasting this against
so the now moving to Pearl a little bit
let's sort of try to understand what the
main difference of three text tasks is
and what contrast is everything is sort
of very different from ptex tasks so the
one thing i already mentioned was
pretext tasks always reason about a
single limit at once so the idea is that
given an image you apply a transform to
that image so in this case they are
jigsaw transform and then you give
basically input this transformed image
into a contact and you try to predict
the property of the transform that you
applied so the permutation that you
applied or the rotation that you applied
or the kind of color that you removed
and so on so the pretext asks always
reason about a single image and the
second thing is that the task that
you're performing in this case really
has to capture some property of the
transform so it really needs to capture
the exact permutation that you applied
or the kind of rotation that you applied
which means that the last layer
representations are actually going to Co
vary or sort of vary a lot as the
transform C changes and that is by
design because you are really trying to
solve that pretext task but
unfortunately what this means is that
the last layer representations capture a
very low-level property of the signal so
they capture like things like rotation
or so on whereas what is sort of
designed or what is expected of these
representations is that they are sort of
in Burien to these things which you
should be able to recognize a cat no
matter whether the cat is upright or
that the cat has say you know tend
towards liking by 90 degrees whereas
when you're solving that particular
pretext ask you're imposing the exact
opposite thing you're saying that I
should be able to recognize whether this
picture is upright or whether this
picture is basically tilted sideways so
there are many exceptions in which you
really want these low level
representations to be covariant and I
thought if it really has to do on the
tasks that you're performing and quite a
few tasks in 3d really wants to be
predictive so you want to sort of
predict what camera transforms you have
you're looking at two views of the same
object or so on but unless you have that
kind of a specific application for a lot
of semantic tasks you really want to be
invariant to the transform the reduced
as a to use that input so invariance has
sort of been the workhorse for feature
learning so something makes it which is
a fairly popular handcrafted feature the
eye in SIPP really stands for invariant
and supervised networks for example
supervised dialects nets or supervisors
next they are trained to be invariant
potato augmentation you want it one this
network to classify different crops for
different rotations of this image as a
three rather than ask it to predict what
exactly was the transformation apply for
the input so this is what inspired both
so foil stands for pretext invariant
representation learning where the idea
is that you want the representation to
be invariant or capture as little
information as possible of the input
transform so you have the image you have
the transform version of the image you
feed forward both of these images
through a cornet you have get a
representation and then you basically
encourage these representations to be
similar so in terms of the notation I
was talking about earlier you basically
say that the image I and any pretext
transformed version of this image I are
related samples and any other image is
an unrated sample so in this way when
you train the network this
representation hopefully it contains
very little information about this
transform T and the SU training is in
contrast if learning so contrast a
learning part is to basically you have
save feature V I coming from the
original image I and you have the
feature V IT coming from the transform
version and you want both of these
representations to be the same and the
paper we looked at two different
state-of-the-art
complete x transforms so that is the
jigsaw and the rotation method that I
talked about over here and we also
explored combinations of these
transforms so apply Pacific
rotation at the same time so in some way
this is like multitask learning but
they're not really trying to predict
both disjoint rotation you're trying to
be invariant to Botha conservation so
the key thing that has sort of made
contrastive learning work well in the
past take sort of successful attempts is
really using a large number of negatives
and one of the good sort of paper that
introduced this was this instance
discrimination paper from 2018 which
introduced this concept of a memory bank
and this is powered I would say most of
the sort of recent methods which are
state of the art including more copper
and they're all sort of page I sort of
hinge on this idea of of empty part I
asked you to employ your headphones from
the computer because it's very noisy
because it's the microphone is picked
from the headphones and let's be very
maybe I don't know it's right okay next
an so the memory bank is a sort of nice
day to get a large number of negatives
without really increasing the sort of
compute requirement so what you do is
you store a feature vector per image in
sort of memory and then you use that
feature vector in your contrast if done
so okay let's sort of first talk about
how you would do this entire pearl setup
without using a memory bank so you have
an image I you have an image i T you
feed forward both of these images you
get a feature vector F of VI from the
original image I you get a feature G of
VI T from the transformed versions the
patches in this case and what you want
is the features F and G to be similar
and you want features from any other
image so an unrelated image to basically
be this simpler so in this case what we
now can do is rather then if we want a
lot of negatives we would really want a
lot of these negative images to be
feed-forward at the same time which
really means that you need a
large bat size to be able to do this and
of course a large bat size means is not
really sort of good is not possible on
say unlimited amount of GPU memory so
the way to sort of do that is to use
something called a memory bank
so what this memory bank does is that it
stores a feature vector for each of the
images in your dataset and when you're
doing contrasts of learning rather than
using feature vectors say from a
different a negative image a sort of a
different image in your batch you can
just retrieve these features from a
memory so you can just retrieve features
of any other unrelated image from the
memory and you can just substitute that
to perform contrast of them so in Perl
we divided the objective into two parts
there was a in like a contrast ship term
to bring the feature vector from the
transformed image so G of VI similar to
the representation that we have in the
memory so M of I and similarly we have a
second contrast septum that tries to
bring the feature at for VI close to the
feature representation that we have in
memory so essentially G is being pulled
close to MI and F is being pulled close
to MI so by transitivity
F and G are being pulled close to one
another and the reason for separating
this out was it sort of stabilized
training and we were able to train
without doing this basically the
training would not really converge and
so by separating this out into two forms
rather than doing like direct contrast
if nothing between F and G we were able
to stabilize training and actually get
it working so the way to evaluate this
is basically like by standard sort of
pre training evaluation setup so
transfer learning where we can pre train
on images without labels so the standard
way of doing this is to take a mesh net
throw away the labels and pretend it is
unsupervised and then evaluate using
saiful fine-tuning or using on training
a linear classifier the second thing we
did was also a test purl and its
robustness to images image distributions
by training it on in the wild images so
we just took one
randomly from Flickr so this is the why
FCC data set and then we basically
perform transfer learning episode free
training on these images and then
perform transfer learning on different
data sets so I had a question about the
pole method about the memory bank where
the m wouldnt those like feature
representation stored in the memory bank
be like out of date yeah so they do go a
little bit out of date but in practice
it really does not make that much of a
difference so that this sort of
particular way of updating them using so
M of I is a moving average of the
representation F and that sort of moving
average although it's still it actually
does not matter a lot in practice you
can still continue to use them so
assuming like I I recently read the
paper simpler which you huge bad size
like 8,000 or something so using like
the memory bank approach and and getting
these 8,000 examples and one loss
function is that possible like yes sort
of Cynthia B of doing it really requires
a large pad size because you're getting
negatives from different images in the
same batch whereas if you use something
like the memory bank you really do not
need a large batch size so you can train
this with like 32 images in a batch
because all the negatives are really
coming from the memory bank which does
not really require you to do multiple
key forwards
okay thank you very using memory bank
till you can't back propagate to the
negative example so is that not the
problem all right in it does not create
that much of a problem
really so that was one thing I was
worried about as well so in the initial
versions we did tie something which was
like using a larger bad size
but it when we switch to something like
the memory bank it did not really reduce
performance very very little very much
in the reduction in performance yeah any
intuition why that's the case so I think
overall contrastive learning is fairly
slow to converge so all like all markets
NCR index the latest version of moko and
so on all of them train for very large
number of epochs
in even so the number of bad props that
you're getting or the number of memory
sort of parameter objects that you're
doing a very large in general so the
fact that you miss out on one of them in
this particular case probably does not
have that much of an effect Thanks
that's five minutes good almost there so
yeah we basically I evaluate those on a
bunch of different tasks so the first
thing was object detection again sort of
standard tasks in vision and in this
case who was able to outperform image
net supervised training on detection for
both the VLC or seven and seven plus
twelve data sets and it outperforms on
this sort of most strict evaluation
criterion which is 80 all which is now
introduced by cocoa which was already
sort of a positive sign and then it was
able to do this the second thing we
looked at was basically evaluating pearl
on semi-supervised learning and once
again pearl was performing fairly well
it was actually better than say the
pretext task of jigsaw so the only
difference between the top row and the
bottom row is the fact that pearl is an
invariant version whereas jigsaw is a
covariant version
and in terms of linear classification
when Pearl came out it was basically at
par with CPC is latest version and was
performing fairly well on a bunch of
different like parameter settings and a
bunch of different architectures of
course now you can have like fairly good
performance by methods like synth here
so that number for simply responding
would basically be about 69 or 70
compared to like Perl 63 years number
the other thing we looked at was
basically how sort of generalizes across
data distributions so for this we looked
at just Flickr images from the biopsy
see data set and who was able to sort of
outperform methods that were trained
using hundred times more data so the
jigsaw row in the second set like a
jigsaw Oh which is the second row was
chained on 100 million images
whereas Pearl was restrained and 1
million images and despite that it's
actually able to sort of outperform the
jigsaw method fairly easily this again
shows you the power of in like sort of
breaking invariance into your
representation rather than sort of
predicting pretext asks
and finally the sort of thing I started
out with which is that whether this
thing is actually semantic so if you
look at different layers of
representations so convent - rs.5 jigsaw
basically shows a drop in performance
from restful to rs5 but as for pearl you
it's all see a sort of nicely increasing
graph whereas for and rs5 get
increasingly more and more semantic in
terms of problem complexity pearl was
very good at handling that because
you're never predicting the number of
permutations you're just using them at
input as like sort of data augmentation
so pearl can sort of scale very well to
all the 360,000 possible permutations in
the nine patches but as for jigsaw
because you're predicting that you're
very limited by the size of your output
space and the paper also shows that we
can extend pearl to not just like it's
not limited jigsaw you can do that on
rotation if you can inside do it in a
combination of jigsaw and rotation and
you can get more and more gains but you
basically start doing this so basically
if you look at these methods
starting from pretext asks to clustering
to pull as you go from the left to the
right you basically get more and more
invariants and in some way you also see
an increase in performance which sort of
suggests that baking in more and more in
various your methods is actually going
to be more helpful in the long term
there are some shortcomings which is
basically that we really do not
understand what is the set of data
transforms that matter so jigsaw works
really well but it's not very clear why
this is happening so some sort of future
work or if you want to spend your spare
cycles thinking about something is
really understanding what imbalances
really matter when you are trying to
solve a supervised task what in there is
really matter for something like image
net and that's it
so basically predict more and more
information and try to be as invariant
as possible thank you so I had a
question yes these contrastive networks
they can't use the batch norm layer
right because then information would
pass from one sample to the other and
then
network might learn a very trivial way
of separating the negatives from the
positive like so it like for Pearl for
example we really did not observe that
phenomenon at all so we did not really
have to do any special tricks with
Bachner we were able to use batch no
masses okay and it's not necessary for
all the contrast if networks to not be
using batch norm it's okay to have the
batch norm here it's yeah it's ten I
mean for example for Cynthia and so on
they try and move the sink batch norm
because if want to emulate a large batch
size so you might have to do some tweaks
in batch norm but basically if you you
cannot avoid it clearly because if you
completely remove batch norm then
training these like very deep networks
is generally very hard anyway okay do
you think that Paul paper works with the
Bashan omnious because it uses a memory
bank and all the representations are not
taken at the same time whereas I think
moco they specifically mentioned not to
use the batch norm layer or use it
spread across multiple GPUs so that that
I think is one difference for sure
because basically the negative side
you're contrasting against and the
positive from different time steps which
makes it harder for batch norm this sort
of cheating but as for the other methods
like moco and same fear they very
correlated to the particular batch that
you're evaluating right now okay so is
there any suggestion if we are using a n
pair loss rather than a memory bank is
there any suggestion how to go about
this whether we should just stick to
Alex Ned and me Gigi which don't use a
batch norm layer or is there any way to
turn it off or so what so can you
describe the setting a little bit more
so basically what I'm trying to do is
train on a frames of videos and I'm
using a n pair setting where I'm trying
to contrast between n samples rather
than two or three samples okay and what
I'm worried about is whether I should be
using batch norm or not and if I am not
using batch norm at all then which pre
brained
sorry pre architectured models can I use
let's Ricky so the one problem with
video frames is basically that fairly
correlated so in general bache norm a
sickly the performance of Bashan on B
grades and you have fairly correlated
samples so video that becomes more and
more a problem
the unfortunate sort of like the sad
news is basically that even like if you
look at a typical implementation of Alex
nineties days it will include batch now
it's just because it's much more stable
to train with that you can train with a
higher learning rate and a lot you can
basically use it for a bunch of
different downstream tasks so I think
you may still have to use batch no it's
not you can give other variants like
group norm try which basically do not
really depend on the batch size ok makes
sense
thank you okay thank you so much he Shan
there's a lot of no interesting details
I think we still have like eight minutes
if people are I think they're like still
many left in class any questions yep I
had been question which I had also put
forward in my lecture when we were
discussing Perl so this question is
about the lowest function can I answer
right now okay so when I read the paper
so there was a probability term that we
were computing after computing the VI
and the vit representation for image and
the transformed version and after
getting those probabilities then we were
using a noise contrastive estimation
loss so I was kind of confused that want
it had been better if just a negative
log of that probability had been
minimized so you can use both really so
the reason to use and C was basically
more to do with how the memory bank
paper was set up so and C you would if
you have K negatives you are basically
solving k plus 1 problems so the one
problem is based you basically have K
plus 1 different binary problems that
you
so that's one way of doing it the other
way of doing it is basically what is now
called info NC which is really the
softmax so you just supplier softmax and
you minimize the negative slope
likelihood for that it's because that
edge the probability function looked
like Softbank so yes in so at the time
and I had tied it out it actually gave
me slightly worse results and so that's
basically why you can see and this was
just initial experiments now when I'm
trying it out it actually gives me save
the results so I guess in the end it
does not make that much of a difference
yam this is more related to the course
but we are gonna have a project on sell
soup was Lonnie stern warning can you
give us information on how to get it get
us sell soup wise Lonnie model walking
as in the implementation details like
the simpler the John the high overall
high level ideas so try to get it
working quickly so I think I mean there
are certain class of techniques that are
going to be much easier to get working
from the get-go right so for example if
you were looking at just three text
tasks then you would basically look at
something like rotation because okay
it's a very easy task to implement you
really cannot go wrong with it but I
mean there are just very few things I
mean so just the number of moving pieces
a good indicator the other thing to
remain remember is basically if you're
sort of implementing a existing method
then there are going to be lots of tiny
details the authors talk about so for
example the exactly learning rate that
they used or the way they used bash norm
and so on
if there are lots of these things then
basically it's going to be harder and
harder for you to sort of reproduce more
and more things for you to get wrong the
second thing to remember is data
augmentations rate augmentations are
really critical so if you get anything
working you would try to sort of add
molded augmentations to it
I think and do you recommend us trying
Oh Lord you cannot be too difficult to
do in one month I'm not sure what the
setting is really some notch okay thanks
when it is one more ting of did you try
using momentum contrast on coal instead
of MD Bank I happened
so we basically move to the end-to-end
version which is like similar to what
Cynthia is so the thing is I mean you
can may see me gather a bunch of
negatives wrong on different GPO so in
case your pad size that actually
generally helps a lot I would suspect
more covert helped a lot as well I think
no Co but improved performance over
Sinclair by replacing end-to-end
training with moco but I think numbers
are still fairly similar and there are
small differences in evaluation protocol
that you would sort of see across these
papers so yeah I think so we're learning
to sort of release a more standardized
evaluation benchmark so we did that last
year unfortunately that was in cafe - so
we're trying to sort of crazy something
in five dots now we provide a lot of
standardized implementations so like
further and a bunch of these and a
standardized evaluation protocol I found
I had a question about above this cell
supervised learning so what do you think
is the state of like generative methods
and did you think about combining like
contrasting methods with generative
methods like simpler actually like has a
different space so they have like a
linear layer on top of the feature
representation where they compute the
actual reach the representation where
they did the contrast loss the NCE stuff
so like do you think like having another
head like that basically given like a
crop of image you just try to scale out
that crop of image and you have that
information because you crop that image
right and use them again or something so
I mean it is definitely a good idea I
think it says the tricky part is getting
these things
just non-trivial so initially like I
haven't really tried any relative
approaches in my experience that's
slightly worse when you can harder to
get to work
but I do agree I think sort of in the
longer term they are like they are sort
of the things to focus on
thank you gasps question no that's it I
guess oh I can actually ask the question
well yeah so this is regarding
distillation actually so you were
telling me how predicting software
distributions gives gives a richer
target right so can you elaborate on
that because it sort of increases the
uncertainty of our model right we are
predicting from one hot distribution and
then making it software and then we are
predicting on that so more uncertainty
and more over like why do they call it
distillation because I saw to feel like
you need more parameters to account for
this richer richer target right so the
one thing is basically if you train on
one hot labels your models tend to be
very overconfident in general so if you
have heard of these tricks called like
label smoothing which is sort of now
being used by a bunch of methods label
smoothing is like you can think of it
like the sort of simplest version of
distillation
so you have a one hot vector that you
were trying to predict but rather than
trying to predict that and Taiwan not
vector what you do is you take some
probability mass out of that so you
would predict one and a bunch of 0s so
rather than doing that you predict say
0.97 and you add point one point one
point one two I'll take the remainder
three vapors she just start a uniform
distribution to the remainder so
distillation is a sort of more informed
way of doing this so rather than like
randomly sort of increasing the
probability of a random undulated class
to actually have a network which was pre
trained which is pretty good to this in
general software distributions are very
useful for free training methods because
models tend to be overconfident
pre-training on like software
distribution is actually slightly easier
than optimization problems you converge
slightly faster as well so both of these
benefits are present in the solution and
also also because like smooth labels
allow you to have like a dog looking cat
or a cat looking dog right so if you
have a very big network that has been
trained on very many samples it will
actually
have you no idea a proper idea of what
is you know unambiguous perhaps image
right and therefore if you can actually
learn that soft idea you're gonna be
learning more than if you just give that
you know one hot label I think we are
time I think we're around the time like
half an hour ago but this was the
question answering question and answers
session
if there are no you know really really
urgent questions still pending I will be
calling it called the end of the today
lesson so thank you for tuning in I see
you tomorrow at the practically
practical session don't forget to come
and it was it so thank you so much
Asian and I see you around execution
thank you everyone take care everyone
right bye-bye
you